A Guide to the Virginia Secretary of Transportation: Correspondence and Subject Files, 1972-1979
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia Secretary of Transportation: Correspondence and Subject Files, 1972-1979
The Library of Virginia
31228
7 cu. ft. (7 boxes)
Virginia. Office of the Secretary of Transportation
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accession 31228 was transfered from the Office of the Secretary of Transportation on 20 October 1981.
Biographical Information
In 1970, the Governor's Management Commission Study recommended the creation of six "Deputy Governors" to assist the Chief Executive in his managerial duties. Compatible functions of government were grouped under these administrative heads, who would serve as the Governors top management team or "secretariats," as they are called now.
Governor Linwood Holton's top priority for the 1972 session of the General Assembly was a proposal for a Governor's Cabinet, reorganizing state agencies into six major departments--each headed by a secretary appointed by the governor. Transportation and public safety was one of these six departments. The office of Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was created on April 8, 1972, by an act passed by the General Assembly. Governor Holton appointed Wayne A. Whitham, a member of the Winchester City Council, as the first Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety. When Whitham took office on July 1, 1972, he was responsible for State Highway Commission, Division of Motor Vehicles, Department of State Police, Highway Safety Division, Office of Emergency Services, Department of Military Affairs, Virginia State Crime Commission and the Law Enforcement Officers Training Standards Commission. The Office has undergone a series of administrative reorganizations since. On April 12, 1976, the Legislature established separate secretariats for transportation and for public safety, effective July 1, 1976. On July 1, 1984, the offices were again combined. Most recently, the Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was divided into separate secretariats on February 22, 1990. The Secretary of Transportation is a member of the Governor's Cabinet, and is appointed by the governor, subject to confirmation by the General Assembly. The Secretary is responsible to the governor for the Department of Transportation, Department of Rail and Public Transportation, Department of Aviation, Department of Motor Vehicles, Virginia Port Authority and the Motor Vehicle Dealers Board.
Wayne A. Whitham, the first Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety, was reappointed by Governor-elect Miles E. Godwin, Jr., in December 1973 and by Governor-elect John N. Dalton in December 1977. Whitham suffered a heart attack in August 1978 and resigned in December 1978. On June 7, 1984, Whitham died in Richmond, Virginia. Governor Dalton named George M. Walters, a former top executive of the Reynolds Metals Corporation, to succeed Whitham as Secretary of Transportation. Walters served until the end of Dalton's term in January 1982. Governor-elect Charles S. Robb, the first Democrat to be elected governor since 1965, did not retain any of Dalton's cabinet secretaries. Robb appointed Andrew B. Fogarty, Dalton's assistant secretary for financial policy, as Secretary of Transportation. On July 1, 1984, the secretariats of transportation and public safety were combined again. As a result this partial reorganization of state government, Governor Robb appointed Fogarty Secretary of Administration and Franklin E. White, Secretary of Public Safety, assumed Fogarty's Transportation duties. White, who served as a White House liaison official under President Jimmy Carter, resigned in June 1985 to become the New York state commissioner of transportation. He was replaced by Andrew Fogarty who served until the end of the Robb administration. He later served as Governor Gerald L. Baliles chief of staff from August 1986 to October 1989 when he resigned to become a vice president with CSX Corporation.
In December 1985, Governor-elect Gerald L. Baliles, picked Vivian E. Watts, a northern Virginia legislator, as Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety. Watts served until the end of Baliles' term in 1990. In 1995 she was elected to her old seat in the Virginia House of Delegates. On February 22, 1990, the Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was divided into separate secretariats. Governor L. Douglas Wilder, appointed John G. Milliken, a member of the Arlington County Board of Supervisors, as the Secretary of Transportation. Milliken resigned on December 17, 1993.
In February 1994 Governor George Allen, the first Republican elected governor since 1977, appointed Robert Martinez as Secretary of Transportation. Martinez was born in Cuba and had served as Deputy Administrator for the Marine Administration and Associate Deputy Secretary of Transportation during President George H.W. Bush's administration. At the end of Governor Allen's term in January 1998, Martinez joined the Norfolk Southern Corporation. Shirley Ybarra, deputy Secretary of Transportation in the Allen administration, was named Martinez's successor by Governor-elect James Gilmore. Ybarra previously worked as a special assistant to Transportation Secretary Elizabeth Dole during President Ronald Reagan's administration. Ybarra served until the end of Gilmore's administration in January 2002. Whittington W. Clement, a former lawyer and long-time member of the Virginia House of Delegates representing the City of Danville, was appointed Secretary of Transportation by Governor Mark R. Warner in 2002. Pierce R. Homer, Deputy Secretary of Transportation, replaced Clement in 2005.
Scope and Content
This collection contains general correspondence and subject files for the Virginia Office of the Secretary of Transportation, organized into alphabetic miscellaneous files, other specific subject files such as aviation, military affairs, DMV, energy, rail, VA-09-8001 Technical Study Grant, Human Resources Agency Transportation Study, and VA-09-8003 Technical Study Grant.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Correspondence and Subject Files
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files, 1972-1979., Extent: 7 boxes. (Box 1-7)
  The original order of files has been maintained as they were recieved from the agency, which are generally arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Miscellaneous A, 1972-1978. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous B, 1972-1978. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous C, 1972-1978. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous D, 1972-1978. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous E, 1972-1978. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous F, 1972-1978. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous G, 1972-1978. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous H, 1972-1978. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous I, 1972-1978. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous J, 1972-1978. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous K, 1972-1978. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous L, 1972-1978. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous M, 1972-1978. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous N, 1972-1978. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous O, 1972-1978. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous P, 1972-1978. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous Q, 1972-1974. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous R, 1972-1979. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous S, 1972-1978. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous T, 1972-1978. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous U, 1972-1975. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous V, 1972-1978. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous W, 1972-1978. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Aviation, Department of (Transition - Effective 7/1/79), 1979. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Aeronautics, Division of, 1972-1979. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Emergency Services - General, 1972-1978. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Highway Safety Division - General (Became Transportation Safety - 7/1/78), 1972-1979. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Highways and Transportation, Department of - General, 1972-1979. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Military Affairs, Department of - General, 1972-1978. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Military Affairs, Department of - Pendleton Property/Right-of-way HB631, 1978. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Motor Vehicles, Division of - General, 1972-1979. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Department of Motor Vehicles: Headquarters Building, 1979. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Motor Vehicles - Lease/purchase Agreement - Headquarters Building, 1979. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Department of Motor Vehicles: Branch Office Personnel Classification Change, 1974-1977. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Department of Motor Vehicles Personnel, 1979-1980. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Virginia Port Authority - General, 1978. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Audit, Internal - State Agencies, 1979. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Aviation, Senate Sub-Committee (Commerce Hearings), 1975. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Aviation, House Sub-Committee (Public works and transportation Hearings), 1976. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Aviation - Deregulation (Regulatory Reform), 1977-1979. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - British Airways, 1976. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - 1979 Energy: Division of - State Office of Energy and Emergency Services (General), 1979. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Energy: Coal: Capabilities of Virginia Meeting, 1979. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Energy: Coal: Va Coal and Energy Commission, 1979. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Energy: Gasoline Coupons - State Ration Reserve Plan, 1980. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Energy Division: Comprehensive State Energy Plan, 1979-1980. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Energy: U.S. Department of Energy - Temperature Emergency Building (Temperature Restrictions), 1979-1980. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Energy: U.S. Department of Energy - Power Plant and Industrial Fuel Use Act (Facilities), 1979. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - False Cape State Park, 1974-1980. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Federal Disaster Assistance Administration, 1979. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Greene County Courthouse - Expolsion and Fire, 1979. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Handicapped and Elderly, 1972-1980. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Hazardous Materials Transportation - Ad Hoc Committee, 1979-1980. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Highway Leg - Federal Highway Beautification Assistance Act, 1979. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Hillsboro, Tow of, 1979. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Ivanhoe Industrial Site (Carroll and Wythe Counties), 1980. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Joint Legislation Audit Review Committee - Federal Funds Study (HJR 237 General Assembly), 1979. (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Jones, Richard H. (Aviation Matters), 1979. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Kilmarnock, Virginia - Post Office (Parking Problems), 1979-1980. (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Metric System, 1979. (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Motorcycles, 1974-1978. (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - National Air and Space Museum, 1978-1979. (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Newport News Marine Terminal, 1978-1979. (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Norfolk, Baltimore and Carolina Line Inc. (NBC), 1979. (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Payne, John K. Re: Southern Railroad Crossing Accident, 1979-1980. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Norhtern Virginia Transportation Commission, 1971-1979. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Rail: AMTRAK - National Railroad Passenger Corporation, 1972-1980. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Rail: Penn Central Car Float (Little Creek/Cape Charles), 1973-1977. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Rail: Scenic Railroad (Gate City/Washington County), 1979. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Shirley Highway - Bus/Carpool Reversible Express Lanes, 1972-1979. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Southeastern Virginia Planning District Commission, 1972-1978. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Rail: T.C.C. Rail Service Planning Office, 1974-1979. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Rail: L and N Railroad - Coal Hauling, 1976. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Thalhimers, 1977-1979. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Virginia Visitor Travel Survey, 1979. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Virginia Resource Information System (HJR 175), 1978. (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - WMATA - Signing Ceremonies Bond Guaranty and Compact Amendments, 1972. (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - VA-09-8001 Technical Study Grant and Human Resources Agency Transportation Study, 1976-1978. (Box 6,)
    - No. 1 Contract Negotiation, 1977-1979. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - No. 1 (a) Work Program - originals, 1977-1979. (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - No. 1 (b) Work Program - less budget, 1977-1979. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - No. 1 (c) Governor's Office Form Budget 16 and Grant Application, 1977-1979. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - No. 2 Contract and Budget Amendments, 1977-1979. (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - No. 3 Federal Guidelines and Forms, 1977-1979. (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - No. 4 Grant Payments, 1977-1979. (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - No. 5 Charges Against Contract, 1977-1979. (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - No. 6 Time and Activity Reports, 1977-1979. (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - No. 7 Financial Reports, 1977-1979. (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - No. 8 Project Status Report, 1977-1979. (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - No. 9 General Correspodence, 1977-1979. (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - No. 10 the Impact of Transportation on Delivery of Human Services, 1977-1979. (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Work Element II - Charlottesville, Va., 1977. (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Work Element II - Farmville, Va., 1977. (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Work Element II - Brief for Secretary Jean Harris, 1977-1979. (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Work Element II - 1976, 1976. (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Work Element II - 1977, 1977. (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Work Element II - 1978, 1978. (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Work Element II - Texarkana Transportation Project, 1977-1979. (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Governor's Council on Transportation: VA-09-8003 UMTA Technical Study Grant, 1976-1977., Extent: 1 box. (Box 7,)
    - Work Element II - Charlottesville, Va., 1977-1979. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Governor's Council on Transportation - UMTA Technical Study Grant, 1976-1977. (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Governor's Council on Transportation (SJR 56), 1976-1977. (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Final Report, 1976-1977. (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Recommendations - Summary of 1977 Report, 1976-1977. (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - 1976 Report - December, 1976-1977. (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Consultants (Worden and Risbert Inc., Philadelphia, Pa.), 1976-1977. (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - General Correspondence - Budget, 1976-1977. (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - General Correspondence - Federal Grant, 1976-1977. (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - General Correspondence - Financial Reports, 1976-1977. (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - General Correspondence - legislation Proposed, 1976-1977. (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - General Correspondence - Furniture and Equipment, 1976-1977. (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - General Correspondence - Meetings, 1976-1977. (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - General Correspondence - Presentation to Hopkins Commission, 1976-1977. (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - General Correspondence - Governor's Council on Transportation Members, 1976-1977. (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - General Correspondence - Progress Reports, 1976-1977. (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - General Correspondence - Consultants' Presentation to Joint Senate Finance and transportation Commitees, 1976-1977. (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - General Correspondence - Travel Vouchers, 1976-1977. (Box 7, Folder 18)